Guide to the Dorothy O. Helly Research Files for Livingstone's Legacy: Horace Waller and Victorian Mythmaking TAM.161
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dorothy O. Helly Research Files for Livingstone's Legacy: Horace Waller and Victorian Mythmaking
circa 1850s-1985
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Helly, Dorothy O.
TAM.161
12 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dorothy O. Helly in 2004. The accession number associated with this gift is 2004.022.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dorothy O. Helly (1931-) is a distinguished historian and (as of 2010) is Professor of History and Women's Studies at Hunter College and The Graduate School at the City University of New York (CUNY). She also has been involved with various academic women's organizations, such as Women Writing Women's Lives. Helly's best known work is Livingstone's Legacy: Horace Waller and Victorian Mythmaking (1987), which analyzes Horace Waller's editing of Livingstone's journals.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of photocopied documents and notes that Helly accumulated during her research for Livingstone's Legacy. Most of the documents are from archives in the United Kingdom, as well as some from archives in Southern Africa. The collection also contains copies of related scholarly works.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Boxes 3 and 4 contain microfilm.
Imperialism |x History |y 19th century; Africa, Southern |x History.; Historians -- United States.; Livingstone, David, 1813-1873; Waller, Horace, 1833-1896; Helly, Dorothy O.; Helly, Dorothy O.
- Inventory
  - Note Cards with Handwritten Notes, NLS - Grant Papers, Livingstone Papers, National Museum of Zambia, The Waller Papers, Chronologies, Individual Papers some on Microfilm, Notes taken from Individual Papers, University of Witwatersrand: Mission Statements, National Archives of Rhodesia Materials, Letters and Depositions, South African Archives, Notes and Journal Articles, 1861-1961 (Box 1)
  - Individual Files: Devaux, Jules Jean-Paul, Evan-Smith, Col. Sir Chas., Huntington, Collis P., Hutchinson, Gen. George, Hutton, James E., Jephson, A.J. Mounteney, Johnston, Sir Harry, Kemall, Sir Arnold B., Kirk, Sir John, Lambert, Leon, De La Laing, Count, Undated (Box 2)
  - Microfilm, Correspondence, Kirk and Stanley Files, Publications; Quarterly Reviews, Munger Africana Library Notes, Letters of Bp Tozer ed. G Ward, Additional Letters and Materials from the National Library of Scotland, 1862-1976 (Box 3)
  - Microfilm, Publications and Testimonials late-19th Century, East Africa Letters, Conference Papers on Women in East Africa, Central African Missionary Diaries, Mailings from Libraries, Letters, Livingston Files, Undated (Box 4)
  - Livingston Letters, Waller Papers, UMCA "Occasional Paper", Proctor Letters, Newspaper Clippings, National Library of Scotland Files, Mrs. Ware's Collection, Mackenzie Letters, Miscellaneous letters from UMCA, Waller Diary, Central African Mission Reports, Files on Slavery, late-19th Century to early-20th Century (Box 5)
  - Mailings, Correspondence Charts, Blackwood's Papers, Rev. Fortnightly and Isaac Taylor, UMCA Files, Northamptonshire Record Office Files, Wylde, William A. Papers, Strauch, Colonel Papers, Rholles House PIKE MSS re Masas'i, 1870s-1880s (Box 6)
  - UMCA Executive and Sub Committee Minutes, Journal Articles, Book Chapters, Land Tenure Information, Files on Malawi, Christian History of Africa, Working Papers in Southern African Studies, 1850s - 1970s (Box 7)
  - Rev. Lovell J. Protecter Files, Missionary Publications: 19th-Century, UMCA Reports, University Mission to Central Africa, Letters, Diary Entries, Sunday Magazine Articles, Journal Articles: Proceedings of the Society of Antiquaries of London, UMCA Paper Reports, John Murray and Hoarce Wallek Publications, MacKennon Papers, Livingston Letters from Zambia, National Library of Scotland Files, St. Anthony's Files, W D Cooley Files, Dr. Livingston Lectures, 1850s - 1880s (Box 8)
  - Stewart Papers from University of Capetown Library, Catalogue of David Livingston Documents, Pamphlets on Asian Labour Migration to Zimbabwe, Microfilm of Individual Papers, John Waller Files, UMCA, American Philosophical Society Grant and Application, National Archives of Rhodesia files (Stewart Papers), Unpublished Papers on Livingston and African Colonialism, UMCA Files letters from Bp. Tozer, Handwritten Notes, Archival Outlines, Photographs: Etchings, Drawings, and Captured Images of Missionary Work, Activity and Portraits in Africa, William MacKennon Papers (SOAS), National Library of Scotland Microfilm, Andrew Roberts Files, Africans Waller from Donald Simpson, 1860s-1985 (Box 9)
  - Handlist of the Papers of Sir Wm. MacKinnon, Baronet, A/S Report Volumes 1 - 2, Church Congress Files, Rev. Henry Rodney Files, 1850s - 1880s (Box 10)
  - Handwritten Notes and Letters taken from the Rhodesia House, British Empire Files, John Murray Archives and Correspondence, UMCA Archives, Missionary Reports and Publications, Journal Articles and Quarterly Reviews, UMCA Papers, National Library of Scotland Files, 1860s-1880s (Box 11)
  - Individual Files: Lee, Henry Austin, Lister, Sir T. Villers, Long, James, MacDonald, John, Lorne, Marquis of, Maitland, W.I., Pelly, Sir Lewis, Sanford, Henry S., Stanley, Sir Henry M., Strauch, Colonel, Undated (Box 12)